Guide to the George F. Emmons Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George F. Emmons papers
1828-1850
WA MSS 166-169
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(7 volumes)
Emmons, George F. (George Foster), 1811-1884
George Foster Emmons (1811-1884)
George Foster Emmons was born at Clarendon, Vermont, on August 23, 1811. His father, Horatio, served throughout the War of 1812 as an officer in the army. George Foster Emmons was appointed a midshipman in 1828 and studied at the New York Naval School. He served on the frigate Brandywine in the Mediterranean, 1830-33, and in 1838 joined the U.S. Exploring Expedition under the command of Charles Wilkes. Emmons served as acting lieutenant of the Peacock, the second ship of the squadron, and stayed with that vessel until it was destroyed at the mouth of the Columbia River. In the fall of 1841, while on the Wilkes Expedition, Emmons led an exploring party overland from the Columbia south to San Francisco. He later served on the Boston of the Brazil Squadron and the Ohio of the Pacific Squadron. While on duty in Washington from 1850 to 1853, Emmons wrote The Navy of the United States from the Commencement, 1775 to 1853, with a Brief History of Each Vessel's Service and Fate. During the Civil War, he served in the Gulf, on the Mississippi River, and in the South Atlantic blockading squadron. In 1868, he was commissioned commodore and spent the rest of his active duty on shore, chiefly as head of the Hydrographic Office in Washington and as commandant of the Philadelphia Navy Yard. Retired as rear-admiral in 1873, Emmons resided at Princeton, New Jersey, until his death in 1884.
Scope and Contents
The George Foster Emmons Papers have been organized in four sections. The first section (WA MSS 166) consists of three manuscript journals (931 pages long) which Emmons kept while attached to the U.S. Exploring Expedition under the command of Charles Wilkes. Emmons wrote the journals while on board the U.S. Sloop of War Peacock, W. L. Hudson, Commander, August 12, 1838 to June 10, 1842. The journals contain an account of the expedition with detailed descriptions of the special surveys made by the Peacock, original drawings of the harbors, and a number of small drawings and diagrams. They are further illustrated by the insertion of portraits, engravings, maps, and extracts from Charles Wilkes' Narrative. Journal No. 3 contains a detailed account of the overland expedition that Emmons commanded from Vancouver to San Francisco, August to October, 1841. Emmons' account of the overland expedition is supplemented by that of Henry Eld (WA MSS 161). A number of letters and documents are inserted chronologically in the journals.
The second section of the Emmons Papers (WA MSS 167) consists of two sketchbooks of original drawings made by Emmons while on board the Peacock during the U.S. Exploring Expedition. The thirty-four drawings to be found in the sketchbooks include sketches of icebergs in the Antarctic, harbors entered, incidents of the voyage, pictures of native peoples, etc. A list which provides a brief description of each drawing is appended below.
The third section (WA MSS 168) consists of a scrapbook of official letters received from 1828 to 1850. Other documents and memorabilia, such as military orders, invitations, and calling cards are also included. The scrapbook contains ninety-seven pieces in all and is organized chronologically into three groups: 1828-37; correspondence relative to the U.S. Exploring Expedition, 1836-38; and 1842-48.
The fourth section of the Emmons Papers (WA MSS 169) consists of a single scrapbook (thirty-four pages long) of mounted clippings from the New York Express, reporting the proceedings of the Naval General Court Martial on board the U.S. Ship North Carolina, at New York, July 27 to September 15, 1842. The clippings cover the trial of Charles Wilkes (August 17), who was accused upon his return from the Exploring Expedition of illegally punishing some of his men. The clippings also cover the trials of Midshipman William May, Lieutenant Robert E. Johnson, Surgeon C. F. B. Guillou, and Lieutenant Robert F. Pinkney which preceded the Wilkes trial, as well as a few trials which followed. (Wilkes was publicly reprimanded by the Court Martial.) There are also a few clippings on miscellaneous topics in the volume.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Courts-martial and courts of inquiry -- United States; Antarctica -- Pictorial works; California -- Description and travel; Oceania -- Description and travel; Oregon -- Description and travel; Washington (State) -- Description and travel; Diaries -- United States; Drawings -- United States; Seamen -- United States; Oceania -- Pictorial works; Emmons, George F. (George Foster), 1811-1884; Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877; Peacock (Sloop of war: 1828-1841); United States. Navy -- History -- 19th century; United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842)
- Journals, 1838-1842; WA MSS.166
  General note
  The following letters and documents are inserted chronologically in the journals.
  Emmons, George Foster. Letter to S. P. Lee. February 23, 1839. True copy, signed S. P. Lee. 1 p.
  Emmons, George Foster. Five letters to Lieutenant Wilkes. February [25], 1839-April 20, 1842. Copies. 6 pp.
  Emmons, George Foster. Letter to Captain Hudson. April 6, 1840. Copy. 2 pp.
  Emmons, George Foster. Letter to J. P. Couthouy. November 14,1840. Copy. 1 p.
  Court Martial, U.S.S. Peacock. Trial of Sweeney, Ward, and Riley, October 2-28, 1840. Charges and specifications preferred by Lieutenant George F. Emmons. Finding and sentences of the Court. Copy. 22 pp.
  Plan of wedding party and guests, January 10, 1843. 2 pp.
  Family of Frances Thornton (Mrs. Emmons), l p.
  Alden, James. Letter to Emmons. August 23, 1845. 2 pp.
  Bacon, Frederick A. Note to Emmons. [February 20 ? 1839.] 1 p. With note added by Emmons.
  Baldwin, Augustus S. Letter to Emmons. [December 19, 1839.] 1 p.
  Carpender, E. W. Letter to Emmons. June 14, 1842. 1 p.
  Carr, Overton. Letter to Emmons. December 29, 1842. 3 pp.
  Case, August Ludlow. Letter to Wilkes. April 20, 1842, signed by A. L. Case, G. F. Emmons, and W. M. Walker. Copy. 1 p.
  Chandler, William. Letter to Emmons. January 9, 1843. 1 p.
  Couthouy, Joseph Pitty. Letter to Emmons. November 10, 1840. 1 p.
  Dana, James Dwight. Letter to Emmons. August 15, 1841. 1 p.
  Dayton, A. O. Notification from Treasury Department, August 23, 1842, to Emmons. Printed form. 1 p.
  DeHaven, Edward Jesse. Letter to Emmons. December 28, 1842. 1 p.
  Drayton, Harry J. Letter to Emmons. January 10, 1843. 1 p.
  Dyes, John W. W. Receipt for elk and antelope horns. October 29, 1841. 1 p. Letter to Emmons. June 10, 1842. l p.
  Fisher, Peter, Lieutenant, Royal Navy. Note to Emmons. [December 7, 1839.] 1 p.
  Gilchrist, Edward. Note to Emmons. [December] 9 [1838]. 1 p.
  Guillou, Charles F. B. Letter to Emmons. November 23, 1841. 1 p.
  Harwood, Andrew A. Letter to Emmons. June 21, 1842. 1 p.
  Hudson, William L. Seven letters to Emmons. October 21, 1839-August 2, 1841. 12 pp.
  Orders to Officers of Peacock, June 21, 1841. 1 p.
  Orders to Emmons. [August 4, 1841.] 1 p.
  Johnson, Robert E. Letter to Emmons. October 20 [1841]. 3 pp.
  Lee, Samuel Phillips. Letter to Emmons. February 23, 1839. 1 p.
  Linn, Lewis Fields. Letter to Emmons. January 6, 1843. 2 pp.
  McKay, Thomas. Letter to Emmons. [September 6, 1841.] 2 pp.
  McLoughlin, John. Letter to Samuel Taylor. August 5, 1841. 1 p. Letter to Emmons. August 15, 1841. 1 p.
  Magruder, George A. Letter to the Secretary of the Navy [J. K. Paulding] from the petty officers of the Macedonian. April 16, 1838. Copy. Endorsed by Lieutenant G. A. Magruder. 2 pp.
  Maury, William L. Letter to Emmons. September 3, 1842. 2 pp.
  Paulding, James Kirke. Two form letters filled in by hand, enclosing commissions to Lieutenant G. F. Emmons. July 11, 1838, March 2, 1841. 2 pp.
  Pickering, Charles. Letter to Emmons. January 11, 1843. 1 p.
  Reynolds, William. Letter to Emmons. August 3 [?], 1846. 1 p.
  Ringgold, Cadwalader. Letter to Emmons, notifying him of appointment as judge advocate. [February 20, 1842.] 1 p.
  Rogers, Cornelius. Letter to Emmons. August 30, 1841, with note at end by Emmons. 3 pp.
  Saywer, H. B. Letter to Emmons. July 13, 1840. 2 pp.
  Sawyer, R. W. (MRS. H. B.). Letter to Emmons. [July 13, 1840.] 1 p.
  Sickles, J. Frederick. Letter to Emmons. November 14, 1839. 1 p.
  Totten, G. M. Letter to Emmons. July 30, 1841. 2p.
  Underwood, Joseph A. Two letters to Emmons. December 13, 1838, May 3, 1839. 2 pp.
  Upshur, Abel Parker. Letter to Emmons, detaching him from the Vincennes. June 17, 1842. 1 p.
  Upshur, George P. Letter to Emmons. January 15, 1843. 2 pp.
  Waldron, Richard R. Summons to witnesses to a General Court Martial, October 13, 1840. On verso of Emmons to Wilkes, October 8, 1840. Copy.
  Waldron, Richard R. Letter to Emmons. October 20,1841, with Emmons' comment. 2 pp.
  Waldron, Richard R. Letter to Secretary of the Navy. January 10, 1842. Copy. 1 p.
  Walker, William M. Two letters to Wilkes. November 5, 1840, April 20, 1841. Copies. 2 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Seven orders to Emmons. July 14, 1838-October 20 [1841]. 19 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Emmons. October 6, 1840, with copy of answer. Accompanied by Defence of Lieutenant R. F. Pinkney before the Court Martial ... 3 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Lieutenants Walker and Emmons. November 6, 1840. Signature only. 1 p.
  Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Emmons and others. May and copy of answer, with map. 2 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Two letters to Emmons. [October 27, February 20, 1842, appointing him judge advocate at Court of Inquiry, February 21, 1842. 2 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Ringgold. [February 20, enclosing "Inquiries for the Court and Proceedings of the naval court," signed by Ringgold and Emmons. Copy [?] 30 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Walker, Case, and Emmons. April 19, 1842. Copy, with copy of the answer, April 20, 1842, enclosing copy of a letter to the Secretary of the Navy from 41 petty officers of the frigate Macedonian, endorsed and signed by Lieutenant G. A. Magruder, April 6, 1838. 4 pp.
  Wilkes, Charles. Court Martial, Minutes, trials of Sweeney, Ward, and Riley, October 2 28, 1840. 22 pp.
  Scope and Contents
  Three journals kept while on board the U.S. Sloop of War Peacock, W. L. Hudson, Commander, August 12, 1838 to June 10, 1842.
  3 vols. [i.e., 931 pp.] 27-39 cm. Original bindings.
  The journals contain an account of the expedition with detailed descriptions of the special surveys made by the Peacock, original drawings of the harbors, and a number of small drawings and diagrams, and are further illustrated by the insertion of portraits, engravings, maps, and extracts from Wilkes' Narrative.
  No. 3 contains a detailed account of the overland expedition, Emmons commanding, from Vancouver to San Francisco, August-October, 1841, which is supplemented by the journal kept by Henry Eld (see WA MSS 161).
  - Journal kept while attached to the South Sea Surveying & Exploring Expedition on board of the U.S. Sloop of War Peacock. W. L. Hudson Esq. Commander., 1838 August - 1839 December; Journal 1 (Box 1)
  - Journal kept while attached to the South Sea Surveying & Exploring Expedition on board of the U.S. Sloop of War Peacock. W. L. Hudson Esq. Commander., 1840 January - 1841 March; Journal 2 (Box 2)
  - Journal of the overland party, Fort Vancouver to San Francisco, 1841 August-October; Journal 3 (Box 3)
    - Land Expedition, plot plan and key, journal entry, 1841 July 25
    - Fort Umpqua or Fort McKay, journal entry, 1841 September 16
- Sketchbooks, 1838-1842; WA MSS.167
  Two sketchbooks of original drawings made while attached to the South Seas Surveying and Exploring Expedition on board the U.S. Sloop of War Peacock, 1838-1842.
  2 vols [i.e., 31 leaves] 29 1/2 x 22 1/2 cm.
  The 34 sketches include drawings of incidents of the voyage, pictures of the icebergs in the Antarctic, harbors entered, natives, etc.
  - Sketchbook 1 (Box 1)
    General
    List of sketches
    Title-page: Drawings Made While Attached To the South Seas Surveying & Exploring Expedition on board THE U.S. SLOOP OF WAR "PEACOCK" BY GEORGE F EMMONS, with a drawing of the Peacock amid the waves.
    Orange Bay near Cape Horn. 25th February 1839.
    U.S.S. Peacock (with photo of same). Antarctic Sea, 1839.
    Schooner Flying Fish in the Antarctic Ice, 1839.
    Chilean Costumes.
    Aguador: (man astride donkey with two barrels of water -- water-carrier, i.e., aguador.)
    Two islands: Tutuila as seen from the top of Namua off Upolu ...and Namua. [Oct 11-18, 1839].
    Appearance of land at the bottom of Fongaloa Harbour from its mouth. [Oct. 21, 1839].
    Untitled. Bridge over a river in a somewhat mountainous area. See Henry Eld Sketchbook No. 3 for a very similar drawing.
    Upolu. One of the Navigators [i.e., one of the Samoan Islands] from off Saluafata. [Oct 21, 1839]. This drawing is in three parts which would join up to be one if the papers were long enough, and shows various ports on the island.
    4 of the Navigator Group: Savaii, Upolu, Manona, and Aborima. [Oct 21, 1839].
    Moatoa, Valley of the Papeno, Tahiti, 1839. Wild Plantains, Sugar Cane, Guava, Yams, Taro, Bread Fruit, Cocoanut.
    Cascade. Valley of the Papeno, Tahiti. 1839.
    Untitled. Various silhouettes of "natives" and probably English, also supernatural horror creatures.
    King Teapot & his two wives of the Bogen Tribe, New South Wales.
    Bungaree. Chief of the Broken Bay Tribe, Sydney, N.S.W.
    Gooseberry. Widow of King Bungaree.
    Engraving, not a drawing. Turkey presented to Mr. Buchanan on inauguration day.
  - Sketchbook 2 (Box 2)
    Icebergs, Antarctic Ocean. January 15, 1840.
    Mid Lat. 66.40 South. January 24th, 1840. (an iceberg, or island).
    Henry Island, Underwood Group. 1840. [July 1840].
    Harbour of Sa-lu-a-fa-ta, Upolu. 1840.
    Burning of Tye. July 13, 1840.
    Boat fight with the Feegees after the Massacre of our officers at Malolo, July 25, 1840. 29 killed.
    July 26th, 1840. Burning of Sualib on Malolo. [Vibi?]
    2 War Canoes -- Geges -- Captured by the Peacock's 1st C[utler?] Lieut. E. July 26th, 1840.
    Polynesian Trees 1840. (One is a banyan tree).
    Fa-ka-afo, De Wolf's or Bowditch Island. Discovered in the mid-watch on board of the U.S.S. Peacock by G.F. Emmons. [Jan 28, 1841].
    Untitled. Building -- perhaps a church -- amid greenery and low mountains. See Henry Eld's Sketchbook No. 2 for a similar drawing of the same building.
    Untitled drawing plus mounted newspaper clipping describing it as a cenotaph caused to be erected at Mount Auburn Cemetery by the members of the Expedition in honor of four of the men who lost their lives.
    Untitled plan for monument to the memory of Lt. Joseph A. Underwood and Midshipman Henry Wilkes, who were massacred at Malolo Island.
    Untitled. Apparently a different view of No. 13.
    Untitled. Plan for pedestal of the same plus text.
    Two headlands (Island of Madeira) to the Westd of Funchal...and Appearance of the Land to the Nd & Ed of Funchal.
    A View of two natural Rocks upon which Fortifications are constructed, opposite the Anchorage at Funchal. May 1833; and, the Peak of Teneriffe ... June 1, 1833.
- Scrapbook, 1828-1850; WA MSS.168
  - Scrapbook of official letters received from 1828 to 1850, and memorabilia., 1828-1850; WA MSS.168; 97 pieces. 28 cm. (Box 1)
    The following are items within the scrapbook.
    Emmons, George Foster. Resolutions passed at a meeting of midshipmen, addressed to the Naval Lyceum, New York. December 28, 1838, signed by Emmons and 18 others. Copy. 1 p.
    Emmons, George Foster. Letter to Ridgely. December 30, 1833, signed by Emmons and 12 others. Copy. 1 p.
    Emmons, George Foster. Request to Navy Department for lessons in swordsmanship at N.Y. Navy Yard. February 10, 1834, signed by Emmons and 26 others. Copy. 1 p.
    Emmons, George Foster. Certificate of admission to bar in Indiana, May 1836, signed by Samuel Bigger and Williams W. Wick. 1 p.
    Emmons, George Foster. Letter to Glynn. January 28, 1838, signed by Emmons, Hartstene and Reid. Copy. 1 p.
    Emmons, George Foster. Letter to Tattnall. February 15, 1838. Copy. 1 p.
    Appleton, John. Letter to Emmons. May 6, 1847. 1 p.
    Ballard, Henry E. Letter to Emmons. September 20, 1830. 1 p.
    Baltimore Club. Invitation. February 18, 1845, signed by Columbus O'Donnelly. Printed form. 1 p.
    Barron, James. Letter to Emmons. July 12, 1830. Signature only. 1 p.
    Biddle, James. Letter to Emmons. August 8, 1845. Signature only. 1 p.
    Boyle, John. Letter to Emmons. September 8, 1834. Printed form. 1 p.
    Boyle, John. Letter to Emmons. August 6, 1836. Signature only. 1 p.
    Branch, John. Three orders to Emmons. May 16, 1829-August 23, 1830. Signatures only. 3 pp.
    Branch, John. Letter to Emmons. August 26, 1830. Printed form. 1 p.
    Chauncey, Isaac. Four orders to Emmons. August 11, 1828-August 25, 1830. Signatures only. 4 pp.
    Cincinnati College. Letter certifying that Emmons has fulfilled the requirements for the B.L. degree, April 20, 1836. 1 p.
    Claiborne, M. G. L. Letter to Emmons. July 5, 1838. 2 pp.
    Clark, James H. Note on orders from Isaac Chauncey to Emmons. January 25, 1830.
    Dale, John B. Letter to Emmons. April 17, 1838. 2 pp.
    Dayton, A.O. Letter to Emmons. November 14, 1842. Signature only. 1 p.
    Dickerson, Mahlon. Orders to Emmons. November 16, 1836. Signature only. 1 p.
    Downes, John. Orders to Emmons. October 14, 1836. Signature only. 1 p.
    Garrett Society. Appointment of Emmons as Treasurer, September 13, 1676 [sic], with note on verso: "Considered a good joke. G.F.E." Broadside.
    Gillis, James Melville. Two letters to Emmons. July 29, 1833, September 22, Signatures only. 2 pp.
    Glynn, James. Letter to Emmons. October 21, 1837. 3 pp.
    Glynn, James. Certificate with regard to Emmons, May 12, 1838. Copy. 1 p. With copy of Emmons to Pickett, June 4, 1838, on verso.
    Halsey, James M. Letter to Emmons. June 1, 1835. Printed form. 1 p.
    Hartstene, H. J. Orders to Emmons. June 2, 1837. 1 p.
    Hartstene, H. J. Letter to Emmons. June 14, 1838. 1 p.
    Henshaw, David. Letter to Emmons. September 28, 1843. Signature only. 1 p.
    Jones, Thomas Ap Catesby. Letter to Emmons. August 12, 1837, granting leave, endorsed by M. Dickerson, August 14, 1837, with note added by Emmons.
    Jones, Thomas Ap Catesby. Orders to Emmons. October 22, 1837. Signature only. 1 p.
    Kendall, Amos. Two letters to Emmons. June 28, August 6, 1834. Signatures only. 2 pp.
    Kennedy, Edmund Pendleton. Letter to Emmons. August 22, 1833. 1 p.
    Kennedy, Edmund Pendleton. Orders to Emmons. October 22, 1842; revoked, October 24, 1842. Signatures only. 2 pp.
    Le Compte, Samuel W. Letter to Emmons. September 19, 1843. 1 p.
    Markoe [?], Francis, Jr. Letter to Emmons. September 29, 1843, acknowledging gifts to the Naval Institute, Washington. Signature only. 1 p.
    Mason, John Young. Orders to Emmons. October 13, 1846. Printed form. 1 p.
    Mason, John Young. Letter to Emmons. May 5, 1847, granting leave. 1 p.
    Mix, Marvine P. Letter to Board of Examiners. April 18, 1834, recommending Emmons. Signature only. 1 p.
    Ohio Medical College. Certificate of Emmons' matriculation, October 24, 1835, signed by J. Cobb. Printed form.
    Pendergrast, G. J. Two letters to Emmons. October 20, 1843, July 4, 1845. Signature only on latter. 2 pp.
    Perry, Matthew Calbraith. Two orders to Emmons. October 12, 1833, March 10, 1834. Signatures only. 2 pp.
    Perry, Matthew Calbraith. Letter to Emmons. March 26, 1834. Signature only. 1 p.
    Pickett, James Chamberlayne. Seven letters to Emmons. January 12, 1837 - June 8, 1838. Signatures only. With copies of Emmons' answers to two of them. 7 pp.
    Renshaw [?], James. Letter to Board of Examiners. July 8, 1833, recommending Emmons. 1 p.
    Ridgely, Charles Goodwin. Letter to midshipmen attached to the New York station. December 30, 1833. Copy [?] With copy of answer, signed by Emmons and 12 others. 1 p.
    Ridgely, Charles Goodwin. Orders to W. I. McCluney. December 30, 1833. Copy. 1 p.
    Ridgely, Charles Goodwin. Two letters to Emmons. March 24, June 11, 1834. 2 pp.
    Ridgely, Charles Goodwin. Three orders to Emmons. June 6, 1834-May 23, 1843. 3 pp.
    Sawyer, George. Letter to Emmons. May 23, 1838. 2 pp.
    Sawyer, H. B. Three letters to Emmons. December 11, 1837 - July 6, 1843. 5 pp.
    Semmes, Raphael. Letter to Emmons. February 21, 1838. 3 pp.
    Smith, A. Thomas. Orders to Emmons. September 16, 1843, signed also by Ridgely. Printed form. 1 p.
    Smith, Joseph. Letter to Commander H. B. Sawyer. September 16, 1843. 1 p.
    Smith, William. Receipt, to Emmons. October 21, 1842. Signature only. 1 p.
    Southard, Samuel Lewis. Printed form to Emmons. April 1, 1828, appointing him acting midshipman. 1 p.
    Southard, Samuel Lewis. Orders to Emmons. July 18,1828, to attend Naval School in New York, l p.
    Tatnall, Josiah. Letter to Auditor, Treasury Department. August 21, 1837. 1 p.
    Tatnall, Josiah. Letter to Emmons. March 13, 1838. 3 pp.
    Turner, Daniel. Two orders to Emmons. June 6, November 11, 1845. Signatures only. 2 pp.
    Underwood, Joseph A. Three letters to Emmons. April 20—November 21, 1837. 5 pp.
    U.S. Congress, 30th. H.R. 536, June 14, 1848. A Bill... for the Relief of the Heirs and Legal Representatives of Captain Presley Thornton, deceased. [Washington, 1848.] 2 pp.
    U.S. Navy. Midshipman's oath, manuscript copy, signed by Emmons, April 17, 1828. 1 p.
    U.S. Navy. General Order, on uniform dress, May 10, 1820. Printed. 4 pp.
    U.S. Navy. General Order, May 1, 1830. Printed. 4 pp.
    U.S. Navy. Petition to Van Buren from the Navy Yard, January 8, 1838. Printed. 1 p.
    Upshur, Abel Parker. Orders to Emmons. September 1, 1842, endorsed by B. Sawyer. Printed form. 1 p.
    Woodbury, Levi. Four form letters to Emmons. July 11, 1833-June 28,1834. 4 pp.
    Woodbury, Levi. Permission to Emmons to attend Naval School, October 10, 1833. Signature only. 1 p.
    The collection indudes invitations, calling cards, and the following orders, letters, and documents, arranged chronologically in three groups: 1828-1837; correspondence relative to the Exploring Expedition, 1836-1838; and 1842-1848.
- Scrapbook, 1842-1842; WA MSS.169
  - Scrapbook of mounted clippings from the New York Express, reporting the proceedings of the Naval General Court Martial on board the U.S. Ship North Carolina, at New York, July 27 to September 15, 1842., 34 pp. 31 cm. (Box 1)
    In addition to the Wilkes trial, the report covers the trials of Midshipman William May, Lieutenant Robert E. Johnson, Surgeon C. F. B. Guillou, and Lieutenant Robert F. Pinkney, all members of the Exploring Expedition, which preceded the Wilkes trial (August 17), and a few trials following that of Wilkes. There are also a few clippings on miscellaneous topics in the volume.
    "Extracts from the Emmons Journal," describing Fort Vancouver and the courtesy of Mr. Douglas and Dr. McLoughlin, edited by George Thornton Emmons, is published in Oregon Historical Quarterly, 1925, XXVI, 263-273, covering journal entries of July 25 to August 2, 1841. [Coe No. 68.]